Well, hey there and welcome back to
Highlander's History. Now, in this
video, we're going to review every dang
thing you need to know about unit 2 of
AP US history. The time period is 16007
to 1754. Now, the major themes of this
unit have to do with comparing the
different motives and methods that
Europeans used to colonize the Americas.
So, why don't you go ahead and crack
open them brain folds cuz I'm about to
dump some learning into them. Let's get
to it. Now, before we get started, just
so you know, this video is part of a
larger ultimate review packet for AP US
History. It's got everything you need to
get an A in your class and a five on
your exam in May. So if you're
interested in something like that, link
in description below. Okay. So the last
unit dealt largely with the societal
structures that were in the Americas
before the Europeans showed up. And then
we saw how the Europeans, namely the
Spaniard, showed up kind of accidentally
and got their concistador on. And this
unit is going to deal with the Black
Friday sale of all European colonialism
in the Americas as the French and the
Dutch and the British all began
clamoring to stake their claim in the
Americas. But each of these European
states implemented their colonial
project just a little bit differently
based on their colonial goals and their
regional circumstances. So let's look at
each of them. First, let's remind
ourselves about how Spain colonized the
Americas. Now, we talked about this in
unit one, but just for the sake of
comparison, let's remind ourselves. The
Spanish established colonies in the
Americas in order to extract wealth,
both in the form of valuable cash crops
and the actual digging of gold and
silver out of the ground. And they
subjected the native population to this
end. They tried with mixed success to
convert them to Christianity and
introduced a cast system that
reorganized society based on racial
ancestry. Okay. Now, let's have a look
at how the French colonized the
Americas. French colonial policies
differed from the Spanish colonial
policies because the French were more
interested in trade than they were in
conquest, especially the fish and fur
trade. Compared to the Spanish and the
English, of whom I will have more to say
in just a moment, there were relatively
few French people who showed up on the
American shores. Now, despite the first
permanent French settlement in Quebec,
mostly the French established trading
settlements around North America. And in
order to further advance their economic
goals, some French traders married
American Indian wives, which kept
kinship ties alive with some of their
more significant native trading
partners. I don't care who you are.
That's romantic. Hey honey, I just want
you to know that the last week has been
the greatest week of my life. And there
was nobody whom I would rather marry in
order to firm up my trading relationship
with your people than you. So, will you
marry me?
Is that a yes? Anybody understand this
language? And yes, while these marriages
may have been a little transactional for
our taste, that doesn't mean that there
wasn't some mutual benefit that occurred
out of these alliances. For example, the
French fostered some alliances with the
Ojiway Indians and there was some mutual
cultural exchange. The Indians benefited
the French because they could prepare
beaver skins for sale at market and the
French benefited the Indians by
introducing iron cookware and
manufactured cloth. All right, now let's
look at the Dutch and their colonial
goals. In6009, the Dutch established a
fur trading center on the Hudson River,
which is in present day New York. And
their goals for colonizing were mainly
economic like the French. Now, the Dutch
were altogether Protestant, but unlike
the Spanish, they showed very little
interest in converting the natives to
Christianity. By 1624, they had
established New Amsterdam, which
facilitated and advanced their economic
goals. And this became a hub of trade
that attracted large populations of
traders and merchants and fishermen and
farmers. Okay, now we need to turn our
attention to the British and their
colonial project. And arguably, it's the
British and their colonial goals that
are the most relevant for United States
history. So, first let's talk about the
motivations for British colonization.
And then we'll compare the different
kinds of colonies that they set up on
the eastern coast of North America. Now,
economically during this period, Britain
was, to put it mildly, a hot mess. The
Columbian Exchange was changing the
economy. Wars with France and the
conquest of Ireland were costing them a
fortune. And as a result of all that,
inflation began to take hold of the
British economy. If you don't know what
inflation is, it just means that prices
were rising and that means their money
was worth less. It just wouldn't buy as
much. And this was particularly grievous
to the noble class who could see their
wealth vanishing before their eyes.
Additionally, the lower classes were
enduring hardship as well. The land
which had always been available to them
for farming was rapidly disappearing due
to the enclosure movement. So take all
of that, put it in a pot, baby, you got
a stew going. Therefore, the motivations
pushing the British to colonize the
Americas were new economic opportunities
and lands on which they could seek those
opportunities. And there were others in
Britain who wanted to venture across the
Atlantic in order to seek religious
freedom and improved living conditions.
And as it turns out in America, they
found what they were looking for. Okay,
now let's look at each of the British
colonial settlements in North America.
And just for poops and giggles, let's
start with the Chesapeake region. In
1607, the British established Jamestown,
which was their first permanent colonial
settlement in North America. The
founding of the colony was financed by a
newish economic model called a joint
stock company. A joint stock company was
a private business entity in which
several different investors put money
into a pot and then collected profits
when the entity was successful. This is
different than say in Spain whose model
for financing colonization was strictly
through the states. Anyway, that model
of financing gives you some sense of
what Jamestown was all about as a
colony.
Jamestown was purely a profit- seeeking
venture. colonists basically divided
their time between searching for gold
and silver and building military forts
to defend the gold and silver that they
did find. But the beginnings of that
settlement, to put it mildly, were
rough. In the first two years, disease
and famine killed nearly half the
settlers. It got so bad that some of
them resorted to cannibalism just to
survive. And by 1610, seven out of eight
of the settlers were dead. So the
cannibals were wellfed. Sorry, too soon.
Are we laughing about this yet? But in
1612, they stumbled upon a miracle.
Colonist John Ralph began experimenting
with tobacco cultivation and that led to
a complete reversal of their fortunes. A
huge influx of investment came when
tobacco was found to be marketable. Now
I should say that most of the people
doing the work on the cultivation of
these crops were indentured servants
which was the major labor system in the
colonies at that time. Now indentured
servants were just people who in general
couldn't afford passage from Britain to
the new world and so they signed a labor
contract that paid for that passage and
they agreed to work for usually 7 years
and then after that they would go free.
So as the demand for tobacco began to
increase, there was a corresponding
demand for the land on which to grow
that tobacco. And when white folks
needed more land, they had a habit of
taking it from the native populations.
And needless to say, that increased the
tension between the two groups. This
increasing encroachment on their land
and the violence that came with it led
Indians to retaliate and raid colonial
farms. These raids, of course,
infuriated the British settlers and they
appealed to their governor, William
Berkeley, to send troops to keep them
safe. And when Berkeley refused, we get
a little event called Bacon's Rebellion.
A settler named Nathaniel Bacon led
angry poor farmers, including indentured
servants, in an attack against the
Indians, and then turned their militia
toward the plantations owned by Governor
Berkeley. They burned plantations, did
incredible amounts of damage, but
ultimately the rebellion was squashed.
Now, the consequence of all this is that
the planter elites got a healthy dose of
fear with respect to disgruntled
indentured servants, and that made them
want to stop leaning on the broken staff
of indentured servitude and lean more
heavily on African slavery. More on that
later. All right, that's the Chesapeake
region. Now, let's talk about the New
England colonies, which were a little
bit north of the Chesapeake, and they
were altogether different. In 1620, it
was settled by pilgrims who migrated in
family units in order to establish a
society, not a profit- seeeking
enterprise. Their goals were bound up in
their Christian religion, and they
created family economies as farmers.
Even though their goals were different,
they still had a rough time like their
brethren and sister to the south. Fevers
and disease killed about half the
original settlers. But after a few
years, they had established themselves a
thriving colonial economy that included
agriculture and commerce. All right, now
let's turn our attention to the colonies
in the British West Indies and the
Southern Atlantic coast colonies. In the
1620s, the British established permanent
colonies in the Caribbean in places like
St. Christopher, Barbados, and Nevice.
There the warm climate afforded them
year round growing seasons. They grew
tobacco, of course, because it was a
staple cash crop. But by the 1630s,
falling tobacco prices led to the
introduction of a new crop, sugarcane.
And sugarcane was wildly popular in
Europe. And so the demand for it spiked.
However, sugarcane is a very
laborintensive crop. And so along with
the increase in demand for sugarcane
came the increase in demand for African
slaves to grow that sugarcane. The
demand for enslaved people grew so much
that by 1660 in Barbados, for example,
the population on that island was more
black than it was white. And yet another
result of all this was a stringent set
of laws that were passed in order to
govern the black population on the
island. These laws defined enslaved
people as property and governed every
little detail of their lives. Now, the
Carolina colonies were influenced by
this system as they set up their own
economy and labor system. Planters from
the Caribbean migrated to South
Carolina, for example, and sought to
make a copy of the Caribbean system in
the Carolinas. And that's exactly what
they did. All right. Now, let's take a
little jaunt up to the middle colonies
and see what's going on there. In New
York and New Jersey, there was a diverse
population. It was on the sea and it was
shot through with many rivers so that
these colonies thrived on an export
economy mainly of cereal crops. And
because of this success, there was this
growing inequality between the classes.
There was an emerging elite class that
was mostly wealthy urban merchants and
there was a lower working class that was
made up of laborers, orphans, widows,
the unemployed, etc. And there was a
significant population of enslaved
Africans. Also in the middle colonies,
we got Pennsylvania. It was founded by
the Quaker and pacifist William Penn.
And in this colony, religious freedom
for all was recognized. And the land on
which colonists farmed was obtained not
by force from the Indians, but mainly by
negotiation with them. Now, the
governance in the colonies was unusually
democratic during this time. Due to
Britain being across the sea and
generally letting the colonies do their
own thing, the colonial leadership
established self-governing structures.
And let me give you some examples. First
is the Mayflower Compact. Pilgrims
signed this before they disembarked from
their ship, the Mayflower, which
organized their government on the model
of a self-governing church congregation.
The second is the House of Burgesses in
Virginia. It was a representative
assembly which could levy taxes and pass
laws. And there are other examples of
representative assemblies throughout the
colonies. But what you really need to
know about them is that where they did
exist, they were dominated by the elite
classes. New York assemblies were
dominated by wealthy landlords. In the
southern colonies, these assemblies were
dominated by elite planters. Okay, so
that's our survey of the different
regions that the British colonized. But
now we need to think about them as a
whole entity with respect to their role
in trade in the Atlantic trade system.
In the late 17th and the early 18th
centuries, trade truly became global.
With the uptick of colonization in the
Americas, a new Atlantic economy was
developed as well. And one of the more
significant manifestations of this was
the triangular trade. And if you just
had to guess, what shape do you think
this trade route resembles? Uh,
triangle. That's correct me from that
side of the screen. Merchant ships would
follow a three-part journey on this
trading route. Let's start in New
England, where merchants would carry rum
to West Africa, where they would trade
it for enslaved people. Then the ships
sailed the dreaded Middle Passage in
which their holes were packed to a cruel
and unhealthy measure with enslaved
cargo. Eventually they made their
landfall in the West Indies where they
traded the slaves for sugarcane. Then
they took that sugarcane right back up
to New England where they sold the
sugarcane which was made to use rum and
the whole show started all over again.
Okay, that's one aspect of how the
Atlantic economy worked. But now let's
pop the hood and see what made that baby
tick. It was an economic system called
mercantalism. Now, those who saw the
world through this economic lens thought
there was only a fixed amount of wealth
in the world. And since they measured
wealth by gold and silver, technically
they were correct. And each state's goal
was to gain as much of that wealth as
possible. And the way that they did that
was by maintaining what they called a
favorable balance of trade, which is to
say more exports than imports. And that
makes sense because if a nation is
exporting goods, that means that gold
and silver is coming in. Now, this
mercantalist system relied heavily on
establishing colonies because that's
where the raw materials came from. And
to that end, the British government
tried to weave more tightly the center
of the empire with the colonies of the
empire. And one way they did this was
through something called the Navigation
Act. This set of laws required merchants
to engage in trade with English colonies
and Englishowned ships. Also, certain
valuable trade items were required to
pass exclusively through British ports
where they could then be taxed. Now,
this is going to cause some problems in
the next period, but for now, we'll
leave it there. The point is, this newly
established Atlantic trade system
changed the colonies. It generated
massive wealth for the elites like
merchants and investors and plantation
owners. And it also turned America's
seapports into thriving urban centers.
Okay, that was trade in the new system.
Now we need to turn our attention to
slavery in the British colonies. Between
1700 and 1808 about 3 million enslaved
Africans were carried on British ships
across the middle passage. The majority
of them were sold into the hands of
planters in the British West Indies. But
it's important for you to know that
every British colony participated in the
slave trade, mainly because of the
extraordinary wealth they gained by
coerced labor in the export economies
dedicated to tobacco, sugarcane, and
indigo. Now, comparatively, New England
farmers held relatively few slaves. The
Chesapeake and Southern colonies, on the
other hand, held lots of slaves. In
Virginia, following the Carolinas and
Barbados, strict slave codes were
introduced, and in these slaves were
defined as cattle, which is to say
property. Additionally, slavery was
turned into a perpetual institution that
was handed down from one generation to
the next. And they did this out of a
desire to keep a more controlled and
growing labor force because indentured
servants and enslaved Native Americans
simply could not supply the demand that
they needed. However, it's going to be
important for you to know that some
enslaved blacks didn't just accept this
system. They actually rebelled and
resisted. And the resistance basically
came in two different flavors. There was
covert and there was overt. Among the
strategies of the covert resistors were
the insistence to secretly maintain
cultural customs and belief systems from
their homeland. Others broke tools,
ruined stored seeds with moisture or
faked illness. And among the strategies
of the overt, I'll give you one
significant example, the Stono
Rebellion. This occurred in South
Carolina in 1739. A small group of
slaves stole weapons from a store and
killed its owners. And then they marched
along the Stoneo River, and their
numbers grew as they marched. Along the
way, they burned plantations and killed
white folks. The South Carolina militia
finally confronted them and squashed the
rebellion, but not before losing many of
their own number. Okay, so the
relationship between the colonist and
the black population was a little bleak,
but I'm sure the colonists have figured
out by now how to make friends with the
Indians. Yeah. No. Now, in the last
unit, I mentioned the Pueblo revolt
against the Spanish. And this led to the
Spanish making some concessions to
American Indian culture. And with the
British, relationship with the Indians
wasn't much better. Case in point,
Metacom's war in 1675, which the British
called King Phillips War. So Metacom was
the chief of the Wampenog Indians and
the British called him King Phillip. He
began to see that the British
encroachment on their ancestral lands
would destroy their way of life. And
therefore the British must be forced
out. And so the Wenog allied themselves
with other Indian groups and attacked
white settlements throughout New
England. They burned fields, killed men,
and captured women and children. The
British allied themselves with the
Mohawk Indians who eventually ambushed
and killed Metaccom, and the movement
fizzled out. But the point is, all was
not well between the British colonists
and the Indians. Okay. Now, in the last
section of this review, we need to talk
about colonial society during that time
and its structure. And let's start with
religion. And if we're going to talk
about religion, we need to start with
the Enlightenment. The Enlightenment was
a movement in Europe, especially among
the elite that emphasized rational
thinking over tradition and religious
revelation. In other words, people
wanted to rely on their thinkythinky
parts at the expense of their believ.
Now, this movement took root in the
colonies largely because of a robust
transatlantic print culture. And that
print culture spread the ideas of
enlightenment thinkers like John Lockach
and Voltaran and Manuel Kox. Now, while
this movement certainly undermines
scriptural and religious authority, and
I'll talk about that more in a moment,
it did introduce to the colonies some
ideas like natural rights. And the idea
of natural rights is that people have
inborn rights given to them by a creator
and not by a government. There was also
the idea that the best form of
government involved checking and
balancing power and that the best way to
achieve that was to split the government
into three branches. The legislative,
the executive, and the judicial.
Additionally, the colonists encountered
ideas like the social contract, which
argued that people were in a contract
with their government. Since the power
to govern is in the people's hands,
their job was to take some of that power
and deliver it to the government. And in
exchange, the government's job was then
to protect the natural rights of the
people. And if the government broke that
contract, it was the people's right to
overthrow that government. All right.
Now, let's talk about the
Enlightenment's attack on religious
authority. A group of Christian colonial
ministers who became known as New Light
clergy lamented the loss of faith
engendered by the Enlightenment. And so
they began to preach against such
abandonment. They also emphasized the
democratic principles of the Bible. They
railed against the practice of elites
buying pews and churches which were
exclusively reserved for them. And as
their work caught on, it led to a
leveling out of society. And the work of
these new light preachers laid the
groundwork for one of the most
significant religious and social
upheavalss of that time, namely the
Great Awakening. The Great Awakening was
a massive religious revival that swept
through all the colonies and generated
intense Christian enthusiasm. And two
notable leaders in this movement were
Jonathan Edwards and George Whitfield.
Edwards was a New England minister who
preached in Northampton with the
precision of a philosopher and the heart
of an evangelist. And under his
preaching, the revival began to catch.
But it was only local at that point. It
took the English itinerant evangelist
George Whitfield to come make the fire
spread. This fiery preacher traveled
throughout all the colonies, preaching
in churches and in open city squares and
in fields and wherever he could gather
people. The result of the great
awakening was a large-scale return to
the Christian faith and an experience
that bound the colonists together. And
many people point to the great awakening
as the first vestigages of a true
American identity and where the seeds
were sewn for the rejection of the
British. So all that to say the great
awakening had a massive impact on
political and social realities in the
colonies. Now also during this time the
colonies were experiencing a gradual
Anglicanization, which is to say they
were becoming more English-like. They
were developing autonomous political
communities that looked very much like
the political communities back in
England. Even so, the colonists began
experiencing a rising frustration with
the British and they began to resist.
Now, all of that is going to be explored
in its fullness in the next unit, but
now I just need to give you an example
of one of the practices that led to that
growing mistrust between the colonists
and English. And there's lots of
examples that I could choose, but I'll
just choose one. The practice of
impressment. And impressment wasn't
like, "Yo, man, that's a nice hat.
Where'd you get that hat?" No,
impressment was the act of seizing
colonial men and then forcing them to
serve in the Royal Navy. Now, England
justified this practice because they
needed soldiers for all their wars, and
they needed colonial troops because,
hey, this empire ain't going to rule
itself. Needless to say, colonial men,
on the other hand, weren't big fans of
the common experience of a Royal Navy
sailor. There was plenty of
malnutrition, disease, and death. And in
1747, a general impressment for King
George's war led to three days of
rioting and resistance in the colonies.
And the important point is this. The
colonies were becoming increasingly
aware of their natural rights and were
refusing to allow their natural rights
to be violated by England. And that's
what you need to know about unit 2 of AP
US history. If you want help getting an
A in your class and a five in your exam,
you know what to do. Click that ultimate
review packet and go get it. If you want
to join the Himler family and give me
the signal that you want me to keep
making these videos, then go ahead and
hit that subscribe button and come
along. He la.